<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS/DTD Docbook XML V4.2//EN" "c:/Program%20Files%20(x86)/Corel/WordPerfect%20Office%20X5/xml/DTD/DocBook4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- Generated by WordPerfect(R) 15 -->
<book>
<chapter label="Chapter1">
<title></title>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para>Article 12</para>
<para>Municipal Labor Relations</para>
<para></para>
<para>(As Last Amended by Ord. 04-822)</para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para>Published by</para>
<para>Baltimore City Department of Legislative Reference</para>
<para>Avery Aisenstark, Director</para>
<para>2010</para>
<para></para>
<para> </para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para>  </para>
<para>              </para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para> For information or to order &#8210; call, write, or fax:</para>
<para></para>
<para> Department of Legislative Reference     </para>
<para>  626 City Hall                         </para>
<para> Baltimore, Maryland 21202            </para>
<para> Tel: (410) 396-4730  &#9742;  Fax: (410) 396-8483</para>
<para></para>
<para>Table of Subtitles</para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para>     Subtitle 1.   Definitions; General Provisions </para>
<para>     Subtitle 2.   Office of Labor Commissioner </para>
<para>     Subtitle 3.   Reserved Rights </para>
<para>     Subtitle 4.   Certification and Recognition of Employee Organizations </para>
<para>     Subtitle 5.   Labor Negotiations </para>
<para>     Subtitle 6.   Dues; Service Fees </para>
<para>     Subtitle 7.   Unfair Labor Practices </para>
<para>     Subtitle 8.   Negotiated Grievance Procedures </para>
<para>     Subtitle 9.   Union Activities </para>
<para>     Subtitle 10.  Professional and Supervisory Units</para>
<para>Table of Sections</para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para>Subtitle 1</para>
<para>Definitions; General Provisions</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 1-1.  Definitions.</para>
<para>&#167; 1-2.  Findings and policy.</para>
<para>&#167; 1-3.  Special employees.</para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para>Subtitle 2</para>
<para>Office of Labor Commissioner</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 2-1.  Office created.</para>
<para>&#167; 2-2.  Duties.</para>
<para>&#167; 2-3.  Staff; expenses.</para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para>Subtitle 3</para>
<para>Reserved Rights</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 3-1.  Employee rights.</para>
<para>&#167; 3-2.  Employer rights.</para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para>Subtitle 4</para>
<para>Certification and Recognition</para>
<para>of Employee Organizations</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 4-1.  In general.</para>
<para>&#167; 4-2.  Determining questions of representation.</para>
<para>&#167; 4-3.  Election of exclusive representative.</para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para>Subtitle 5</para>
<para>Labor Negotiations</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 5-1.  &#8220;Negotiation&#8221; defined.</para>
<para>&#167; 5-2.  Duty to negotiate.</para>
<para>&#167; 5-3.  Negotiators.</para>
<para>&#167; 5-4.  Scope limitations.</para>
<para>&#167; 5-5.  Impasse.</para>
<para>&#167; 5-6.  Selection of Impasse Panel.</para>
<para>&#167; 5-7.  Panel findings and recommendations.</para>
<para>&#167; 5-8.  Time table.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Subtitle 6</para>
<para>Dues; Service Fees</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 6-1.  Dues check-off.</para>
<para>&#167; 6-2.  Service fees.</para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para>Subtitle 7</para>
<para>Unfair Labor Practices</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 7-1  In general.</para>
<para>&#167; 7-2.  Prohibited conduct by employer.</para>
<para>&#167; 7-3.  Prohibited conduct by employee organization.</para>
<para>&#167; 7-4.  Referring complaints to third-party agency.</para>
<para>&#167; 7-5.  Conduct of hearing.</para>
<para>&#167; 7-6.  Decision.</para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para>Subtitle 8</para>
<para>Negotiated Grievance Procedures</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 8-1.  Authorized.</para>
<para>&#167; 8-2.  Alternative procedures.</para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para>Subtitle 9</para>
<para>Union Activities</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 9-1.  When activities permitted.</para>
<para>&#167; 9-2.  Strikes, secondary boycotts, and picketing prohibited.</para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para>Subtitle 10</para>
<para>Professional and Supervisory Units</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 10-1.  Limitation for professional and supervisory units.</para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para>Subtitle 1</para>
<para>Definitions; General Provisions</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 1-1.  Definitions.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)  In general.</para>
<para></para>
<para> As used in this article:</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)  Appropriate unit.</para>
<para></para>
<para> &#8220;Appropriate unit&#8221; means a group of employees recognized as appropriate for representation by
an employee organization.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (c)  Budget submission date.</para>
<para></para>
<para> &#8220;Budget submission date&#8221; means the date by which, under the law, the proposed budget of the
employer is submitted to the City Council by the Board of Estimates for final action.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (d)  Employee.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (1)&#8220;Employee&#8221; means any person holding a position in the service of the Mayor and City
Council of Baltimore, required by Article VII, &#167; 99 of the City Charter to be classified.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (2)&#8220;Employee&#8221; shall not include:</para>
<para></para>
<para>    (i)those employees in the Baltimore City Public School System who are included within
the definition of &#8220;public school employee&#8221; contained in &#167; 6-401(c)(1) of the State
Education Article;</para>
<para></para>
<para>    (ii)employees of the Police Department;</para>
<para></para>
<para>    (iii) part-time (other than regular part-time), seasonal, probationary, provisional, or
temporary employees;</para>
<para></para>
<para>    (iv) employees engaged in personnel work in other than a clerical capacity;</para>
<para></para>
<para>    (v)employees occupying positions which involve a relation of personal confidence
between the one appointing and the one appointed; or</para>
<para></para>
<para>    (vi) those classified employees whose salaries are established by any agency other than
the Mayor and City Council.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (3)In case of doubt, the Labor Commissioner shall determine who is an employee within the
meaning of this article.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (e)  Employee organization.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (1)&#8220;Employee organization&#8221; means any organization which admits municipal employees to
membership, the primary purpose of which is to represent employees concerning terms and
conditions of employment.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (2)&#8220;Employee organization&#8221; shall not include any organization which discriminates because of
race, color, creed, or national origin, with regard to the acquisition or retention of
membership, or in accepting or advancing members in any training, apprenticeship, or
employment program.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (3)No &#8220;employee organization&#8221; shall be certified as the representative of employees in a unit of
professional and/or supervisory employees if such organization admits to membership or is
affiliated in any way with an organization which admits to membership rank and file
employees; however, the provisions of this sentence shall not apply to employee
organizations representing fire officers and registered nurses.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (f)  Employer.</para>
<para></para>
<para> &#8220;Employer&#8221; means the Board of Estimates or any agency of the Mayor and City Council of
Baltimore other than the City Council.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (g)  Grievance.</para>
<para></para>
<para> &#8220;Grievance&#8221; means:</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (1)a dispute concerning the application or interpretation of the terms of a memorandum of
understanding, or</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (2)a claimed violation, misinterpretation, or misapplication of the rules or regulations of a
municipal agency or the employer affecting the terms and conditions of employment.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (h)  Professional employee.</para>
<para></para>
<para> &#8220;Professional employee&#8221; means any employee engaged in work:</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (1)which is predominantly intellectual and varied in character as opposed to routine mental,
manual, mechanical, or physical work;</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (2)which involves the consistent exercise of discretion and judgment in its performance, of
such a character that the output produced or the result accomplished cannot be
standardized in relation to a given time period; and</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (3)which requires knowledge of an advanced type in a field of science or learning
customarily acquired by a prolonged course of specialized intellectual instruction and
study in an institution of higher learning or a hospital, as distinguished from a general
academic education or from an apprenticeship or from training in the performance of
routine mental, manual, or physical processes.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (i)  Secondary boycott.</para>
<para></para>
<para> &#8220;Secondary boycott&#8221; means any activity by an employee organization which is intended to
induce, encourage, or coerce persons doing business with the employer to withhold, withdraw, or
in any respect curtail their business relations with said employer.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (j)  Strike.</para>
<para></para>
<para> &#8220;Strike&#8221; means, by concerted action, the failure to report for duty, the willful absence from one&#8217;s
position, the stoppage or slow down of work, or the abstinence in whole or in part from the full,
faithful, and proper performance of the duties of employment for the purpose of inducing,
influencing, coercing, or preventing a change in compensation or rights, privileges, obligations,
or other terms and conditions of employment.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (k)  Supervisory employees.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (1)&#8220;Supervisory employees&#8221; means those employees having the authority to exercise
independent judgment in the interest of the employer, to hire, transfer, suspend, lay off,
recall, promote, discharge, assign, reward, or discipline other employees, or having the
responsibility to direct them or adjust their grievances, or effectively to recommend such
action, if in connection with the foregoing the exercise of such authority is not of a routine or
clerical nature but requires the use of independent judgment.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (2)Notwithstanding anything herein contained, any employee who receives cash payments for
overtime pursuant to the rules of the Board of Estimates shall not be deemed to be a
supervisory employee, unless said employee is a department head, bureau head, or division
head.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (3)Provided, further, that the provisions of subsection (d) hereof excluding from coverage under
this article employees occupying positions which involve a relation of personal confidence
between the one appointing and the one appointed shall not be applicable to supervisory
employees.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (l)  Terms and conditions of employment.</para>
<para></para>
<para> &#8220;Terms and conditions of employment&#8221; means salaries, wages, hours, and other matters relating
to employee benefits and duties, such as, but not limited to, holidays, pensions, and vacations.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;120.) (Ord. 68-251; Ord. 68-318; Ord. 70-670; Ord. 72-232; Ord. 76-022;
Ord. 04-672.)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 1-2.  Findings and policy.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)  Preventing and resolving controversies.</para>
<para></para>
<para> The City Council finds that unresolved disputes involving employees in the municipal service are
injurious to the public, the municipality, and municipal employees.  Therefore, adequate means
should be provided for preventing controversies between the municipality and its employees and
for resolving them when they occur.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)  Fair treatment of employees.</para>
<para></para>
<para> Because the paramount interest of the public and the nature of municipal governmental processes
make it necessary to impose special limitations upon public employment, it is incumbent upon
the municipality to provide orderly procedures for the participation by municipal employees and
their representatives in the formulation of personnel policies and plans, to insure the fair and
considerate treatment of municipal employees, to eliminate employment inequities, and to
provide effective means of resolving questions and controversies with respect to terms and
conditions of employment, at the same time insuring that the public health, welfare, and safety
will be at all times maintained.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (c)  Cooperative efforts.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (1)To that end, it is necessary in the public interest that the municipal officials, municipal
employees, and their representatives, shall enter into negotiations with affirmative
willingness to resolve grievances and differences.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (2)Municipal agencies and employees and their representatives shall have a mutual obligation to
endeavor in good faith to resolve grievances and differences relating to terms and conditions
of employment with due regard for and subject to the provisions of applicable laws relating to
personnel policies, including hiring, promotion, suspension, discharge, position
classification, and fixing of compensation and any and all other laws, ordinances, and Charter
provisions governing public employment and fiscal practices in the City of Baltimore.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;119.) (Ord. 68-251.)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 1-3.  Special employees.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Anything to the contrary in this article notwithstanding, if the governing body of</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (1)the Enoch Pratt Free Library of Baltimore City, or</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (2)the Baltimore Museum of Art, Inc., or</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (3)the Municipal {Peale} Museum of the City of Baltimore, Inc., or</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (4)the Baltimore City Public School System, or</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (5)the Board of Trustees of the Community College of Baltimore,</para>
<para></para>
<para>determines by appropriate resolution to have the definition of employees contained in &#167; 1-1(d)
extended so as to include any of its employees not within said definition, then said employees of
each such corporation shall be considered for the purpose of this article, employees of the Mayor and
City Council and subject to all of the provisions hereof.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;135.) (Ord. 68-251; Ord. 69-475; Ord. 70-904.)</para>
<para>Subtitle 2</para>
<para>Office of Labor Commissioner</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 2-1.  Office created.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)  In general.</para>
<para></para>
<para> There is hereby created and established the Office of Labor Commissioner of Baltimore City, the
head of which shall be the Labor Commissioner, who shall be appointed by the Mayor in the
manner prescribed by Article IV, &#167; 6 of the Baltimore City Charter and hold office as therein
provided.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)  Initial Commissioner.</para>
<para></para>
<para> Provided that, in the first instance, the term of the person holding the position of Labor
Commissioner at the time of the enactment of this article shall run concurrently with the term of
the Mayor.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;121(1st par.).) (Ord. 68-251)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 2-2.  Duties.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)  Administration of law; rules and regulations.</para>
<para></para>
<para> The Labor Commissioner:</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (1)shall be charged with the administration of the Municipal Labor Relations Ordinance; and</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (2)is hereby authorized and empowered to make any rules and regulations as may be
necessary or proper to put into operation and effect the provisions of this article.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)Advisor.</para>
<para></para>
<para>In addition, he shall act:</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (1)as a permanent member of the employer&#8217;s negotiating team; and</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (2)as advisor to the Mayor and the Board of Estimates on labor relations matters which
directly affect the City of Baltimore.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (c)  Recommendations on law, etc.</para>
<para></para>
<para> The Labor Commissioner shall study and make recommendations with respect to the
establishment, revision, or correction of policies and procedures governing the relations between
the City of Baltimore and its employees, including the activities of the Civil Service
Commission, the Department of Human Resources, and the Board of Estimates, and further make
recommendations with respect to the introduction of ordinances to effectuate these policies.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;121(2nd, 3rd pars.).) (Ord. 68-251; Ord. 04-822.)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 2-3.  Staff; expenses.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)  Staff.</para>
<para></para>
<para>The Labor Commissioner shall employ such other employees as shall be required to effectively
administer the provisions of the within article subject to the provisions of the Baltimore City
Charter relating to Civil Service.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)  Expenses.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Compensation of all persons in the Office of the Labor Commissioner and all other necessary
expenses of the Commissioner shall be paid at such rates and in such amounts as the Board of
Estimates shall approve and in accordance with the appropriation in the Ordinance of Estimates
of Baltimore.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;121(4th par.).) (Ord. 68-251)</para>
<para>Subtitle 3</para>
<para>Reserved Rights</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 3-1.  Employee rights.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Employees shall have, and shall be protected in the exercise of, the right of self-organization, to
form, join, assist, or participate in any employee organization, or to refrain from forming, joining,
assisting, or participating in any employee organization, freely and without fear of penalty or reprisal,
to negotiate collectively through representatives of their own choosing on terms and conditions of
employment subject to the limitations herein stated and the administration of grievances arising
thereunder, subject to the applicable provisions of any law, ordinance, or charter provisions relating
thereto.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;122.) (Ord. 68-251.)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 3-2.  Employer rights.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)  In general.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (1)Notwithstanding any other provision contained herein, it is the exclusive right of the
employer to:</para>
<para></para>
<para>    (i)determine the mission of each of its constituent agencies;</para>
<para></para>
<para>    (ii)set standards of services to be offered to the public; and</para>
<para></para>
<para>    (iii) exercise control and direction over its organization and operations.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (2)It is also the right of the employer:</para>
<para></para>
<para>    (i)to direct its employees;</para>
<para></para>
<para>    (ii)to hire, promote, transfer, assign, or retain employees in positions within an agency;
and</para>
<para></para>
<para>    (iii) in that regard, to establish reasonable work rules.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (3)It also retains the right to:</para>
<para></para>
<para>    (i)suspend, demote, discharge, or take any other appropriate disciplinary action against
its employees for just cause and in accordance with the provisions relating to Civil
Service of employer&#8217;s Charter and other applicable laws; or</para>
<para></para>
<para>    (ii)to relieve its employees from duty in the event of lack of work, funds, or for other
legitimate reasons.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)  Memorandums of Understanding &#8212; section deemed part of contract.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (1)The provisions of this section shall be deemed to be a part of every memorandum of
understanding reached between the employer and an employee organization.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (2)Provided, however, that nothing contained in this section shall be deemed to deny the right of
any employee to submit a grievance as defined in &#167; 1-1(g)(2) hereof.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (c)  Memorandums of Understanding &#8212; subject to Charter and laws.</para>
<para></para>
<para> Any memorandum of understanding reached between the employer and employee organization
shall be subject to the provisions of the Charter or applicable ordinance concerning salaries,
hours of work, fringe benefits, pensions, and other conditions of employment.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;123.) (Ord. 68-251.)</para>
<para>Subtitle 4</para>
<para>Certification and Recognition of Employee Organizations</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 4-1.  In general.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)  Employer may recognize.</para>
<para></para>
<para> The employer is hereby empowered to recognize any employee organization certified as
hereinafter provided as the exclusive representative of the employees in an appropriate unit.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)  Duty to negotiate.</para>
<para></para>
<para>The employer and such employee organization shall have the mutual duty to negotiate
collectively, as hereinafter provided.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (c)  Exclusive right of representation.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (1)When an employee organization has been so certified, it shall have the exclusive right to
represent all employees in the unit for the purpose of collective negotiation, as described
herein, and the handling of employee grievances.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (2)Provided said employee organization shall be responsible for fairly representing the interests
of all such employees without discrimination and without regard to employee organization
membership.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (d)  Employee may grieve individually.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (1)Provided, however, that any individual employee may present a grievance to his employer
and have the grievance adjusted, without intervention of his certified employee organization,
provided the adjustment shall not be inconsistent with the terms of any memorandum of
understanding between the employer and the certified employee organization representing
such employee then in effect.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (2)Any certified employee organization representing such employee:</para>
<para></para>
<para>    (i)shall be given prompt notice of the filing of the grievance;</para>
<para></para>
<para>    (ii)shall have the privilege of attending any hearings; and</para>
<para></para>
<para>    (iii) shall be notified of the adjustment thereon.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;124.) (Ord. 68-251.)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 4-2.  Determining questions of representation.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)  Commissioner to process petition and negotiate.</para>
<para></para>
<para> Whenever, in accordance with the provisions of this article and with such rules and regulations as
may be promulgated by the Labor Commissioner, a petition or petitions have been filed with the
Labor Commissioner claiming that a question concerning representation exists:</para>
<para>   (1)by or on behalf of an employee organization alleging:</para>
<para></para>
<para>     (i)that a substantial number of employees wish said employee organization to be
their exclusive representative for collective negotiation, or</para>
<para></para>
<para>     (ii)that the employee organization currently certified no longer represents the
majority of employees in the unit; or</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (2)by the employer alleging that one or more employee organizations have presented to it a
claim to be recognized as the representative of a majority of employees in a specified
unit,</para>
<para></para>
<para> the Labor Commissioner shall process said petition and negotiate on behalf of the employer, with
the employee organization and any party or parties permitted to intervene in the proceedings, for
the purpose of endeavoring to reach an agreement concerning the question of representation
within 5 days.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)  Governing standards.</para>
<para></para>
<para> In considering the question of representation, the Labor Commissioner shall define the
appropriate unit pursuant to the following standards:</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (1)A unit which consists of a majority of employees in a civil service job classification or
group of related civil service job classifications shall be deemed prima facie an
appropriate unit.</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (2)This shall not limit the power of the Labor Commissioner to determine that a unit other
than one based on job classification is appropriate so long as:</para>
<para></para>
<para>     (i)the description of the unit corresponds to a community of interest among the
employees in the proposed unit, involving such criteria as similarity of job duties,
skills, wages, educational requirements, supervision, hours of work, job location,
and working conditions; and</para>
<para></para>
<para>    (ii)the unit is compatible with the joint responsibilities of the employer and
employees to serve the public.</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (3)No unit shall be deemed appropriate if it includes both professional and other employees
unless a majority of such professional employees vote for inclusion in such unit, nor shall
any unit be deemed appropriate if it includes both supervisory and non-supervisory
personnel.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (c)  Impartial panel to decide unresolved questions.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (1)In the event said Labor Commissioner, employee organization, employer, intervenor, or
intervenors fail to reach an agreement on any aspect of the question concerning
representation, the Labor Commissioner shall refer the dispute for final determination to a
board of 3 impartial persons selected from a panel obtained from an independent third party
agency, agreeable to all parties, and such board, in reaching its determination, shall be bound
by the provisions of this article.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (2)The costs of such determination shall be divided among all parties thereto.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (3)In the event the parties are unable to agree on an independent third party agency, the board
shall be selected from a panel obtained from the Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service
of the U.S. Department of Labor.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;125.) (Ord. 68-251.)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 4-3.  Election of exclusive representative.</para>
<para></para>
<para>(a)  In general.</para>
<para></para>
<para>If a question concerning representation is found to exist, the Labor Commissioner shall direct an
election upon the following bases.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)  No intervenors with 10% or greater representation.</para>
<para></para>
<para> Where an employee organization certifies to the employer that it has a membership enrollment,
as evidenced by dues authorization cards, of at least 30% of the total number of employees in an
appropriate unit, and if no other intervenor employee organization or organizations certifies that
it has a membership enrollment of at least 10% of the total number of employees in said unit,
then, in such event, a secret ballot election shall be held in which the employees in such unit shall
be offered a choice between exclusive representation by such organization or of no exclusive
representation.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (c)  2 or more intervenors with 10% or greater representation.</para>
<para></para>
<para> In the event that an employee organization certifies to the employer that it has a membership
enrollment of, or authorizations to represent at least 30% of the total number of employees in an
appropriate unit and if any intervenor employee organization or organizations certifies that it has
a membership enrollment of at least 10% of the total number of employees in such unit, then in
such event, a secret ballot election shall be held wherein the ballot shall offer a choice among
each of said employee organizations or of no exclusive representation.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (d)  Majority vote prevails.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (1)In all elections held hereunder the employee organization receiving the majority of votes cast
by the eligible employees in a unit shall be declared to be the exclusive representative of all
employees in such unit.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (2)Provided, however, that if the majority of votes in said election is cast for no exclusive
representative, then there shall be no representative designated for such unit.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (3)Provided further, that where none of the choices on the ballot receives a majority, a run-off
election shall be conducted, the ballot providing for a selection between the 2 choices
receiving the largest and second largest number of valid votes cast in the election.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (e)  1 election only per 2-year period.</para>
<para></para>
<para> No election shall be conducted in any unit in which an election has been conducted within the
preceding 2 years.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (f)  Impartial agency assistance.</para>
<para></para>
<para> The services of the State Department of Labor and Industry or any other impartial agency
selected by the parties to the election shall be utilized for the purpose of conducting elections
hereunder including any disputes which may arise in respect thereto.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (g)  Certification of results.</para>
<para></para>
<para> The Labor Commissioner shall announce publicly the results of any election and shall certify said
results.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;126.) (Ord. 68-251.)</para>
<para>Subtitle 5</para>
<para>Labor Negotiations</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 5-1.  &#8220;Negotiation&#8221; defined.</para>
<para></para>
<para> The term &#8220;negotiation&#8221;, as used herein, shall include the duty to:</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (1)confer in good faith at reasonable times, including meetings appropriately related to the
budget-making process; and</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (2)reduce to a memorandum of understanding the matters agreed upon as the result of such
negotiations in the event that all of the issues have been resolved.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;127(2nd par.).) (Ord. 68-251.)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 5-2.  Duty to negotiate.</para>
<para></para>
<para>On certification of an employee organization as the exclusive representative of employees, the
employer and the employee organization have the duty, through appropriate officials or their
representatives, to negotiate collectively with respect to the terms and conditions of employment
of the employees in the unit.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;127(1st par.).) (Ord. 68-251; Ord. 04-672.)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 5-3.  Negotiators.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)  In general.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Negotiations between the employer and the employee organization shall be conducted:</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (1)on behalf of the employer, by a committee to be named by the Mayor, which committee
shall include the Labor Commissioner; and</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (2)on behalf of the employee organization designated as the exclusive negotiating agent for
the employees in the unit, by 2 or more representatives of such employee organization.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)  Chair.</para>
<para></para>
<para>The chairman of the employer&#8217;s negotiating team shall be named by the Mayor.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;127(3rd par.).) (Ord. 68-251.)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 5-4.  Scope limitations.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)  In general.</para>
<para></para>
<para> In the event that the appropriate unit determined hereunder consists of other than a unit of all
City employees or less than a Citywide unit of all employees in a particular job classification or
groups of related job classifications, the scope of negotiations between the employer and
employee organization shall be limited as hereinafter provided.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)  Wage scales that must be uniform.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (1)Negotiations for salaries and wage scales which must be uniform and apply equally to City
employees in like classifications pursuant to Article VI, &#167; 12 of the City Charter shall be
negotiated jointly with all certified employee organizations representing employees within
the said classifications, provided that said certified employee organizations which participate
in said negotiations jointly represent more than 30% of the employees in such classification
or classifications.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (2)If the certified employee organizations electing to participate in such negotiations jointly
represent less than 30% of said employees, salaries and wage scales shall be excluded from
the scope of negotiations.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (c)  Working conditions that must be alike.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (1)Provided, further, that negotiations for working conditions which must be alike for the
employees in the several municipal agencies pursuant to Article VI, &#167; 12 of the City Charter
shall be negotiated jointly with all certified employee organizations representing employees
within the several municipal agencies, provided that said certified employee organizations
which participate in said negotiations jointly represent more than 30% of the employees in
the several municipal agencies.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (2)If the certified employee organizations electing to participate in such negotiations jointly
represent less than 30% of said employees, working conditions shall be excluded from the
scope of negotiations.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (d)  Organizations may choose not to participate.</para>
<para></para>
<para> This provision shall not be construed to require any certified employee organization to participate
in negotiations if it does not choose to do so, but such refusing certified employee organization
shall be barred during the current negotiating period from participating in such joint negotiations.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;127( 4th - 7th pars.).) (Ord. 68-251.)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 5-5.  Impasse.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)  Attempt to mediate.</para>
<para></para>
<para>If after a reasonable period of negotiation over the terms of an agreement, a dispute exists
between the employer and the certified employee organization or organizations with whom it is
negotiating, or if no understanding has been reached within a reasonable period of time, but not
later than March 1, prior to the final date for setting the municipal budget, it shall be deemed that
an impasse has been reached, at which time the Mayor shall request that an Impasse Panel be
selected pursuant to &#167; 5-6 hereof and that the Chairman of the Impasse Panel enter the
negotiations for the purpose of mediating the impasse.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)  Referral for fact-finding and recommendation.</para>
<para></para>
<para>If the said Chairman is unable to mediate the impasse, the matter shall be referred to the entire
Impasse Panel for fact-finding and recommendation.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (c)Exception.</para>
<para></para>
<para>No impasse shall be deemed to have occurred where the employee organization or organizations
which represent the greater number of employees covered by the negotiations have accepted the
employer&#8217;s proposal.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;127(8th, 9th pars.).) (Ord. 68-251.)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 5-6.  Selection of Impasse Panel.</para>
<para></para>
<para>(a)  In general.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Should an impasse be reached in negotiations between the employer and certified employee
organization concerning terms and conditions of employment (as provided in &#167; 5-5 hereof), an
Impasse Panel consisting of 3 persons shall be selected as follows:</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (1)The employer and the employee organization shall each select 1 member within 3 days
after the request for the convening of the panel.  Should there be more than 1 employee
organization involved in the dispute, all said employee organizations together shall be
limited to selecting 1 member.</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (2)The 2 members so selected shall select a third member within 3 days of their selection.  If
the 2 members are unable to agree on the third member, they shall make their selection
from a panel maintained by an independent third party agency agreeable to all parties.  If
the parties are unable to agree on the independent third party agency, the third member
shall be selected from a panel maintained by the Federal Mediation and Conciliation
Service of the United States Department of Labor.</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (3)The Chairman of the panel shall be the member selected pursuant to (2) above.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)  Compensation of members; assessment of costs.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (1)The Labor Commissioner shall provide in his rules and regulations for standard rates of
compensation for the members of the panel for their services, subject to approval by the
Board of Estimates.</para>
<para></para>
<para>(2)The cost of Impasse Panel procedures shall be divided equally between the parties.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;128(a), (b)(3rd par.).) (Ord. 68-251.)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 5-7.  Panel findings and recommendations.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)  &#8220;Fact finding&#8221; defined.</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#8220;Fact finding&#8221;, as used herein, shall include the identification of the major issues in the dispute,
review of the positions of the parties, and the resolution of factual differences.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)Panel to make findings, etc.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Where an impasse has been reached in negotiations, the Impasse Panel shall meet with the parties
and shall make written findings of fact and recommendations for the solution of the dispute.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (c)Factors to be considered.</para>
<para></para>
<para>The panel, in making its findings and recommendations shall take into consideration, among
other pertinent factors:</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (1)wages and fringe benefits paid other City employees;</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (2)wages and fringe benefits paid for like work by private employers in the City of
Baltimore;</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (3)the value of other benefits available to or received by City employees as compared with
private employees in the City of Baltimore;</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (4)cost of living data; and</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (5)the availability of funds.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (d)  Dissemination of findings, etc.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Copies of such findings and recommendations shall be sent to the employer and the employee
organization or organizations.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (e)  Mediation not precluded.</para>
<para></para>
<para> Nothing herein contained shall be construed as prohibiting the Impasse Panel from mediating the
dispute at any time after it is referred to it prior to the issuance of its recommendations.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;128(b)(1st, 2nd pars.).) (Ord. 68-251.)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 5-8.  Time table.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)  Negotiation period; effective date.</para>
<para></para>
<para> Regardless of the date upon which certification is issued to any employee organization,
negotiations shall be held only between January 1 and March 1 of the following year and all
memoranda of understanding reached as a result of such negotiations shall become effective on
July 1 following such negotiations.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)  Submission to Board of Estimates.</para>
<para></para>
<para> Any recommendations contained in the memorandum of understanding reached between the
employer and employee organization as the result of negotiations shall be brought to the Board of
Estimates for its approval by April 1 in order that the Board of Estimates shall have adequate
time to consider the recommendations contained therein in connection with the proposed
Ordinance of Estimates for the ensuing fiscal year.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;136.) (Ord. 68-251.)</para>
<para>Subtitle 6</para>
<para>Dues; Service Fees</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 6-1.  Dues check-off.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)  Authorized.</para>
<para></para>
<para> Any employee organization certified as the exclusive representative of employees in a designated
unit, upon the presentation of dues deduction authorization cards duly executed by individual
employees in said unit, shall be entitled to have such employees&#8217; membership dues deducted
from their paychecks and remitted to the designated employee organization.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)Term.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Such authorization shall be irrevocable for the period of 1 year, and automatically renewable
from year to year thereafter, unless written notice of termination by the employee is given to the
employer at least 30 days prior to the anniversary date.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (c)  Limitation.</para>
<para></para>
<para> An employee organization shall be entitled to such dues deductions:</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (1)only in those units where said employee organization has been certified as the exclusive
representative; and</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (2)only during the period that said employee organization continues to be so certified as the
exclusive representative.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;129.) (Ord. 68-251; Ord. 69-587; Ord. 73-503; Ord. 75-993; Ord. 76-022;
Ord. 96-067.)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 6-2.  Service fees.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)  Contract may authorize.</para>
<para></para>
<para> A memorandum of understanding executed between the Mayor and City Council of Baltimore
and any employee organization certified as the exclusive representative of employees in a
designated unit may contain a provision whereby all employees who elect not to join, or remain
members of, the employee organization certified in their respective bargaining unit, unless
otherwise indicated in the Fiscal Year 1996 Memorandum of Understanding applicable to their
bargaining unit, shall be required, as a condition of employment, to pay a service fee to the
certified employee organization during the period that said employee organization retains its
certification, in an amount not to exceed the then current employee organization dues in order to
defray the costs incurred by the said certified employee organization in the negotiation,
administration, and implementation of the terms of the memorandum of understanding, and all
modifications and amendments thereto, including related proceedings before an Impasse Panel or
arbitrators; in the processing of grievances; in the conduct of disciplinary proceedings and in the
appeal thereof; in the protection and improvement of civil service rights; and in any and all other
proceedings and matters for which the employee organization is the employees&#8217; exclusive
representative as a result of its certification.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)  Payroll deduction.</para>
<para></para>
<para> The service fees authorized by this section shall be deducted from employees&#8217; pay without their
written authorization.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;130.) (Ord. 75-993; Ord. 96-067.)</para>
<para>Subtitle 7</para>
<para>Unfair Labor Practices</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 7-1.  In general.</para>
<para></para>
<para> The following shall be deemed unfair labor practices which are prohibited.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;131(intro).) (Ord. 68-251.)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 7-2.  Prohibited conduct by employer.</para>
<para></para>
<para> The employer is prohibited from:</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (1)Interfering with, restraining or coercing employees in the exercise of their rights of
self-organization or non-organization.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (2)Encouraging or discouraging membership in an employee organization by discrimination in
regard to hire, tenure, promotion, or other conditions of employment; provided, that nothing
in this law shall preclude the employer from including in a memorandum of understanding
with an employee organization certified as the exclusive representative of employees
pursuant to &#167; 4-3 hereof, a provision whereby all employees who elect not to join, or remain
members of, the employee organization certified in their respective bargaining unit, unless
otherwise indicated in the Fiscal Year 1996 Memorandum of Understanding applicable to
their bargaining unit, shall be required, as a condition of employment, to pay a service fee to
the certified employee organization and to have such fee automatically deducted by the
employer from their paychecks as provided in &#167; 6-2 hereof.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (3)Controlling or dominating an employee organization or contributing financial or other
support to it.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (4)Refusing to negotiate in good faith with a certified employee organization.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;131(2nd par.).) (Ord. 68-251; Ord. 75-993; Ord. 96-067.)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 7-3.  Prohibited conduct by employee organization.</para>
<para></para>
<para> Employee organizations are prohibited from:</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (1)Interfering with, restraining, or coercing employees in the exercise of their rights of
self-organization or non-organization.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (2)Inducing the employer or its representatives to commit any unfair labor practice.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (3)Refusing to negotiate in good faith with the employer.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;131(3rd par.).) (Ord. 68-251.)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 7-4.  Referring complaints to third-party agency.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)Complainant may refer.</para>
<para></para>
<para>In the event that a claim is made that an unfair labor practice has been committed by either the
employer or employee organization, the complaining party shall file with an independent third
party agency designated by the Labor Commissioner a verified complaint setting forth a detailed
statement of the alleged unfair labor practice.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)Response.</para>
<para></para>
<para>The party complained of shall have the right to file an answer to the complaint within 5 days after
service thereof.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (c)   Agency&#8217;s options.</para>
<para></para>
<para> After investigation, such agency may:</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (1) issue an order dismissing the complaint; or</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (2)order a further investigation or a hearing thereon at a designated time and place.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;131(4th par.)(1st - 3rd sens.).) (Ord. 68-251.)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 7-5.  Conduct of hearing.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Any such hearing shall be conducted without regard for the strict rules of evidence and a transcript of
testimony shall be taken.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;131(4th par.)(4th sen.).) (Ord. 68-251.)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 7-6.  Decision.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)  Prohibited practice found to have occurred.</para>
<para></para>
<para> If, upon all the testimony, the agency determines that an unfair labor practice has been
committed, it shall:</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (1)state its findings of fact;</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (2)issue and cause to be served upon the party committing the unfair labor practice an order
requiring it or him to cease and desist from such practice within a specified period; and</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (3)take such further affirmative action as will comply with the provisions of this article.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)  No prohibited practice found to have occurred.</para>
<para></para>
<para> If, upon all the testimony, the agency determines that a prohibited practice has not been or is not
being committed, it shall:</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (1)state its finding of fact; and</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (2)issue an order dismissing the complaint.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;131(5th par.).) (Ord. 68-251.)</para>
<para>Subtitle 8</para>
<para>Negotiated Grievance Procedures</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 8-1.  Authorized.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)In general.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Understandings reached between an employee organization which is the exclusive representative
of employees in an appropriate unit and the employer may contain provisions concerning
procedures for consideration and resolution of grievances by binding arbitration.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)Limitation.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Provided, however, that if binding arbitration of a particular grievance would be contrary to any
of the provisions of the Baltimore City Charter, the decision of any arbitrator shall not be final
and binding on the parties but shall be advisory only.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;132(1st sen.).) (Ord. 68-251; Ord. 72-241.)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 8-2.  Alternative procedures.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)In general.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Such procedures shall be in addition to any grievance procedure already established by the Board
of Estimates.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)  Employee option.</para>
<para></para>
<para>(1)The employee shall have the right to choose which method of grievance procedure he prefers.</para>
<para></para>
<para>  (2)Once an employee has elected to pursue a specific grievance procedure, he is bound by his
election and he may not subsequently choose to follow a different procedure.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;132(2nd, 3rd sens.).) (Ord. 68-251; Ord. 72-241.)</para>
<para>Subtitle 9</para>
<para>Union Activities</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 9-1.  When activities permitted.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)  Internal business.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Solicitation of members, dues, and other internal employee organization business shall be
conducted only during the non-duty hours of the employees concerned.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)  Meetings, etc., between management and union representatives.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Employer-requested or -approved consultations and meetings between management officials and
representatives of recognized employee organizations shall, whenever practicable, be conducted
on official time, but negotiations with an employee organization which has been accorded
exclusive recognition shall be conducted during the non-duty hours of the employee organization
representatives involved in such negotiations, if they are employees within the unit.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;133.) (Ord. 68-251.)</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 9-2.  Strikes, secondary boycotts, and picketing prohibited.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)  Strikes or secondary boycotts.</para>
<para></para>
<para> Employee organizations shall not engage in, initiate, sponsor, support, or direct a strike or
secondary boycott.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)  Picketing.</para>
<para></para>
<para> Employee organizations shall be prohibited from engaging in, initiating, sponsoring, supporting,
directly or indirectly, picketing of the employer or any of its property in furtherance of a strike.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (c)  Penalties.</para>
<para></para>
<para> If any employee organization shall violate any of the provisions hereof:</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (1)its designation as exclusive representative, if any, may be revoked by the employer;</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (2)it may be ineligible to participate in elections or be certified as exclusive representative
for a period of 2 years thereafter; and</para>
<para></para>
<para>   (3)the employer may refrain from making payroll deductions for such organization&#8217;s dues
for a period of 2 years thereafter.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;134.) (Ord. 68-251; Ord. 74-770.)</para>
<para>Subtitle 10</para>
<para>Professional and Supervisory Units</para>
<para></para>
<para>&#167; 10-1.  Limitation for professional and supervisory units.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (a)  In general.</para>
<para></para>
<para> Notwithstanding the rights granted employee organizations pursuant to Subtitles 5, 7, and 8 of
this article, an employee organization certified as representative of employees in a unit consisting
of professional and/or supervisory employees is limited in its rights hereunder only to meet and
confer concerning wages, hours, and working conditions and reduce the results of such
negotiations to a memorandum of understanding.</para>
<para></para>
<para> (b)  Exceptions.</para>
<para></para>
<para> The provisions of this section shall not apply to employee organizations representing fire officers
and registered nurses.</para>
<para>(City Code, 1976/83, art. 1, &#167;137.) (Ord. 72-231.)</para>
</chapter>
</book>